Growing up in the South
わたしは人種隔離の時代に
アメリカ南部で育ちました
during the time of segregation
—blacks and whites—
we couldn’t mix.
黒人と白人は隔離されていました
And not only that, they had signs
「白人専用」とか「非白人専用」という
看板があったんです
to keep you knowing
where you were supposed to go.
I couldn’t understand
why we couldn’t get along.
どうして仲良くできないんだろうと
思いました
Fifty cents.
50セント
Yes, Sir.
はい だんな様
Thank you, Sir.
ありがとうございました
Grandma, he’s just a boy.
Why are you saying “Sir”?
おばあちゃん 子どもなのに
どうして「だんな様」って呼ぶの？
Be quiet.
I want you to know your place.
お黙りなさい
白人はわたしたちより上なのよ
トラックに戻ってから祖母に言いました
I told her after we got back on the truck:
“You know what?
I’ll never hold my head down!”
「黒人だからって
下だとは思わないわ！」
My grandmother
knew I had a love for the Bible
わたしは聖書が大好きで
いつも読んでいました
because I would
always read the Bible as a kid.
でも意味はよく分かりませんでした
But I couldn’t understand it.
よく こう祈りました
I used to pray,
“What makes us so different?”
「人はみんな同じじゃないんですか？
You know,
“Why can’t we live together?”
どうして一緒に暮らせないんですか？」
ある組織にかかわるようになりました
I met a group,
and this group was like
what I really wanted to be in.
その組織がすごく気に入ったんです
政治的な組織で
「不公正を正す」と言っていました
They were about politics.
They said, “We’re fighting injustice.”
And when they said
that word “injustice,” it was like,
それを聞いて思いました
「その通りよ！社会を変えて
みんな一致しなきゃ！」
‘Yeah, this is what I want to be in, right?
‘To be part of something that can change
それこそ わたしの目指すものでした
and make people united, right?’
That was my goal.
We started protesting about police brutality,
警察の野蛮な行動に抗議しました
and I think that’s what a lot of people,
その当時
盛んに議論されていた問題でした
you know,
were focusing on.
組織の活動に
賛同できた点もありましたが
I liked some of the things
that they were doing,
毎日やらされた軍事訓練には
参加したくありませんでした
but they trained us every,
every day in military training.
We learned how to use weapons
and stuff like that.
武器の使い方などを
練習させられたんです
And so I’m thinking:
「わたしが求めているのは
こんなんじゃない」と思いました
‘This is not what I want to be in.
This is not what I joined.’
それで 以前のように
聖書を読むことにしました
So I started going back to God again
—to reading the Bible—
その組織にいても
何も変えられないと分かったからです
because it was like
I’m not changing anything.
The Bible that I was reading
was the King James Version.
ジェームズ王欽定訳聖書を読みました
So I was reading it, reading it, reading it,
何度も読みましたが意味が分かりません
but I couldn’t understand it.
We went to Jamaica,
ジャマイカに行った時
初めて「新世界訳聖書」を見ました
and we saw this Bible,
the New World Translation.
And I started reading it,
and it made so much sense!
読んでみると 意味が分かるんです！
And I could understand it,
and it wasn’t “thee” and “thou.”
「汝は」なんて出てきません
感動して「こういう聖書が
欲しい！」と思いました
I was like, ‘Wow!’
You know, like,
‘This is the one I want to get.’
ある日 二人の女性が訪問してきました
One day, two women knocked on the door.
真っ先に目に入ったのは
その人たちの持っていた聖書でした
I didn’t know they were Jehovah’s Witnesses.
All I could see was that Bible.
わたしが「その聖書
どこで手に入るんですか？」と聞くと
And I said,
“Where did you get that Bible from?”
And they said,
“OK, we’ll bring you one.”
「1冊お持ちします」と言われました
And they did.
So they brought me the Bible,
それでやっと「新世界訳」が
手に入ったんですが
but I didn’t know I was going to have
a Bible study that came along with it.
聖書研究も一緒に付いてくるって
知りませんでした
The first time I went
to a convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
初めてエホバの証人の大会に出席した時
it was like ten thousand people.
出席者は1万人くらいだったと思います
When I went in there and I saw
いろいろな顔かたち
肌の色の人たちがいました
all these different faces
and different colors,
まるでエホバが
こうおっしゃったようでした
it was like Jehovah showing me:
“Hey, Rafika, remember you were asking me
「ラフィカ いろんな人種の人たちが
一つになれるようにと祈っていたね？
“about all different people
getting together and being one?
ご覧 わたしは不公平な神ではないんだよ
See, I’m not partial;
they do get along; we are unified.”
And it just made me feel so good inside.
本当にすがすがしい気持ちになりました
Yes!
これこそ わたしが
求めていた組織でした
This is the organization
that I want to be in.
I just see people as people, you know,
みんな同じ人間です
だれにでも伝道して友達になれるんです
and I can preach
and be friends with anybody.
聖書が実際に教えているのは
Now that I know
what the Bible really teaches,
神と神の王国だけが
世界を平和にできるということです
I have a wonderful life
because I know
that only God and his government
それを知って 人生が豊かになりました
can bring about peace.
Just like how Jehovah
unified everybody,
エホバが人を一致させます
I want everybody
to be unified
みんながエホバを知って
一致するよう願っています
and come to know Jehovah,
just like I know him.
エホバはわたしの祈りに
答えてくださいました
Jehovah answered my prayer.